Guide to the Harry Gamboa, Jr. Photographs, 1971-1995
Department of Special Collections
Harry Gamboa, Jr. Photographs,
1971-1995
MSS PHOTO 203
Gamboa, Harry, Jr.
.25 linear ft. (93 black & white prints, 7 original Polaroid instant prints)
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
The 93 B&W prints are unique in that they were hand-printed in 1995 by Willie Garcia along with Gamboa's supervision. Although several of these images have been printed elsewhere, the quality and tonality of these prints will not be reproduced by other photo lab techniques. Several of the negatives were lost. Seven of the 100 photographs are original Polaroid instant prints.
Administrative Information
Access
None.
Acquisition Information
Purchased, 2000.
Biography
Harry Gamboa Jr. was born in 1951, the first of five children born to Harry T. Gamboa and Carmen Gamboa, a working class Mexican American couple. He grew up in East Los Angeles California, an urban area tormented by poverty, violence and racial conflict. Despite these surroundings, the inadequacy of the East L.A. public schools and his parents' lack of education, Gamboa was encouraged to value education and did fairly well in school. As a teenager he was active in community organizations and politics. As a student at High School (graduated 1969) Gamboa was active in student government and as an organizer of various student-initiated reforms, most significantly the 1968 "East L.A. Blowouts" -a series of protests against the inferior conditions of public schools in poor, non-white areas.
Gamboa's extra-curricular activities were not, however, limited to politics. Already a developing artist, it was at Garfield High that Gamboa met Gronk (Glugio Nicondra), Patssi (then Patsy) Valdez and Willie Herrón, three of his closest associates in his later career. After the "Blowouts," for his final year of high school, Gamboa dropped out of the political scene in order to dedicate himself to his education. Thanks to these efforts and with the help of the Equal Opportunities Program (EOP) for disadvantaged minority students, Gamboa was able to attend California State University at Los Angeles. From this point his career as an artist -both solo and with Gronk, Valdez and Herrón in the art collective ASCO (Spanish for nausea)-took off.
Gamboa's work as a writer, photographer, film-maker, performance artist and multi-media creator of "things" is diverse, but in all his efforts (including those as a member of ASCO) his focus has been to reveal the absurdity of urban life and to confront both the dominant white culture and various perspectives within Chicano culture, pointing to the pain and alienation caused by both. This is often achieved by altering the media of the art itself, as opposed to just the subject matter. Gamboa's most significant works include mail art of the 1970s, ASCO's "no movies," the "urban opera" Ignore the Dents and Jetter's Jinx.
Gamboa has one son, Diego, born c. 1980, a product of his first marriage. In 1993 Gamboa married his second wife, Chicano muralist Barbara Carrasco, after seven years of romantic and professional involvement. Their daughter, Barbara Gamboa, was born in 1994.
Collection Scope and Content Summary
The 93 black and white prints are unique in that they were hand-printed in 1995 by Willie Garcia along with Gamboa's supervision. Although several of these images have been printed elsewhere, the quality and tonality of these prints will not be reproduced by other photo lab techniques. Several of the negatives were lost. Seven of the 100 photographs are original Polaroid instant prints.
Access Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Mexican American arts.; Mexican Americans.; Photography.; Photoprints.; Photographers.
Collection Contents
- Antizona (Diego) / (photo by Daniel J. Martinez), 1987 (Box 1, Othertype 1)
- Huevitos (Humberto Sandoval and Barbara Carrasco), 1994 (Box 1, Othertype 2)
- John Valadez, 1986 (Box 1, Othertype 3)
- Barbara Carrasco(during pregnancy)and Gamboa,1994, [Polaroid] (Box 1, Othertype 4)
- Undoings (Irma Garcia), 1994 (Box 1, Othertype 5)
- Humberto Sandoval at OTIS, 1983 (Box 1, Othertype 6)
- Billy Estrada, 1979 (Box 1, Othertype 7)
- Sean Carrillo, 1983 (Box 1, Othertype 8)
- Louis Carios Bemal, 1983 (Box 1, Othertype 9)
- LA. Familia (Humberto Sandoval), 1993 (Box 1, Othertype 10)
- Henry Gutierrez, 1993* (Box 1, Othertype 11)
- Joe Medina, 1993* (Box 1, Othertype 12)
- Evaporations (Paulina Sahagün), 1994 (Box 1, Othertype 13)
- Eliminating the Sky (Anthony C. Sandoval), 1994 (Box 1, Othertype 14)
- Jack Vargas, 1994* (Box 1, Othertype 15)
- Gamboa and daughter Barbara / (photo by Barbara Carrasco), 1995, Polaroid (Box 1, Othertype 16)
- Roberto Bedoya, 1994* (Box 1, Othertype 17)
- Undoings (Moises Corrales), 1994 (Box 1, Othertype 18)
- LA. Familia (Barbz & Diego), 1993 (Box 1, Othertype 19)
- Friday (Teddy Sandoval), 1978 (Box 1, Othertype 20)
- Sons of Soul, 1978 (Box 1, Othertype 21)
- TJ Hooker (TV series gang episode scene shot on location in ELA), 1987 (Box 1, Othertype 22)
- 3 LAPD Cops Arrest I Man, 1981 (Box 1, Othertype 23)
- Culver City Girls, 1979 (Box 1, Othertype 24)
- 3 Boys/UFW, 1979 (Box 1, Othertype 25)
- Cesar Chavez, 1979 (Box 1, Othertype 26)
- Ruby, Richard & Son, 1979 (Box 1, Othertype 27)
- Rodolfo Acuña, Barbz, Edwatd James Olmos, (UCLA meeting related to student hunger strike) 1993 (Box 1, Othertype 28)
- 3 Boys/Skid Row, 1978 (Box 1, Othertype 29)
- Organic vs. Inorganic, 1978 (Box 1, Othertype 30)
- Odd Squad (ELA new wave music group), 1984 (Box 1, Othertype 31)
- Molina & Roybal, 1989 (Box 1, Othertype 32)
- Boy With Cotton Candy, 1979 (Box 1, Othertype 33)
- Baby Barbie, Diego, & Barbz (Silverlake), 1994 (Box 1, Othertype 34)
- America Tropical (SIQUEIROS mural, detail showing chewing gum on eyes), 1979 (Box 1, Othertype 35)
- Children At Work Stuffing Pillows (ELA), 1979 (Box 1, Othertype 36)
- Rudy Perez Jr. and Rudy Perez III, 1979 (Box 1, Othertype 37)
- Miguel Perez, 1981 (Box 1, Othertype 38)
- Arthur Marchand, 1977 (Box 1, Othertype 39)
- Cesar Rosas, 1991 (Box 1, Othertype 40)
- Qctavio Paz, 1984 (Box 1, Othertype 41)
- Sr. Pinhead, 1978 (Box 1, Othertype 42)
- Raises de Sangre (Treviño's movie premiereGolden Gate Theater/ELA), 1979 (Box 1, Othertype 43)
- Francisco Gonzalez, 1978 (Box 1, Othertype 44)
- Javier Perez, 1974 (Box 1, Othertype 45)
- Carlos Montes, 1979 (Box 1, Othertype 46)
- Miltary Police in LA., 1991 (Box 1, Othertype 47)
- Street Preacher, 1985 (Box 1, Othertype 48)
- Culture Clash, 1987 (Box 1, Othertype 49)
- Whittier Quake (Diego), 1987 (Box 1, Othertype 50)
- Girls in costume (ELA), 1977 (Box 1, Othertype 51)
- Chilito, Vanessa, & Beliñda (Diego's FLORES cousins), 1977 (Box 1, Othertype 52)
- HarryT. Gamboa Retirement Party (ELA), 1989 (Box 1, Othertype 53)
- Rodolfo Perez, 1982 (Box 1, Othertype 54)
- Dancers, 1982 (Box 1, Othertype 55)
- Carlos Fuentes, 1984 (Box 1, Othertype 56)
- Max Benavidez, Victor Valle, Tere Romo, Diego Gamboa, Barbara Carrasco at John Vaiadez exhibition reception, (late 1980s), polaroid (Box 1, Othertype 57)
- Undoings (Octavio Gaitan), 1994 (Box 1, Othertype 58)
- Gamboa & Jose Montoya / (photo by Evangelina F. Gamboa), 1977 (Box 1, Othertype 59)
- Patssi Valdez (Cover image, Regeneración), 1974 (Box 1, Othertype 60)
- Gamboa in Mesa, AZ / (photo by Robert Buitron), 1983 (Box 1, Othertype 61)
- Jetter's Jinx (Humberto Sandoval & Gronk), 1985 (Box 1, Othertype 62)
- David Avalos visit to Gamboa class at CALARTS (also pictured Jody Zellen, Franklin Odel, Rick Salazar, and Lyle Ashton Hams), 1989 (Box 1, Othertype 63)
- Zoot Suit Mural (Barara Carrasco & John Valadez), 1979 (Box 1, Othertype 64)
- Void & Vain (Humberto Sandoval & HG) / (photo by Diane Gamboa), 1983 (Box 1, Othertype 65)
- Imperfecto (Lorraine Ordaz, Humberto Sandoval, Debra Term, Sean Carnhlo), 1983 (Box 1, Othertype 66)
- Venom vs Antidote (Diego & Apolina Vargas), 1994 (Box 1, Othertype 67)
- Rene Yañez, RIo, Volanda Lopez, 1981 (Box 1, Othertype 68)
- Undoings (Paulina Sahagün), 1994 (Box 1, Othertype 69)
- OrganIc vs. Inorganic (Rlcardo Gonzalves), 1994 (Box 1, Othertype 70)
- Undoings (Kate Vozoff), 1994 (Box 1, Othertype 71)
- Losers Of The Game, 1980, [PolaroId] (Box 1, Othertype 72)
- Asco8l, 1981 (Box 1, Othertype 73)
- Gronk, Humberto Sandoval, Willie Herron, Diego Garnboa, Gamboa dunng installation of ILLEGAL LANDSCAPE exhibit at CSULA, 1980, [Polaroid] (Box 1, Othertype 74)
- Undoings (Eddie Ayala), 1994 (Box 1, Othertype 75)
- Yreina Cervantez, Frances Salome Espana, Ricardo Gonzalves, Barbara Carrasco, Maria Elena Gaitan, George Silva, Marcos Sanchez, Max Benavidez, and Diego Gamboa. UC Irvine after ANTIZONA performance, [Polaroid] (Box 1, Othertype 76)
- Undoings (Maria Elena Gaitan), 1994 (Box 1, Othertype 77)
- Loner With A Gun (Luis Becerra), 1994 (Box 1, Othertype 78)
- Angst For The Memones, 1994 (Box 1, Othertype 79)
- Undoings (Max Benavidez), 1994 (Box 1, Othertype 80)
- Daniel Villarreal, 1983 (Box 1, Othertype 81)
- Undoings (Del Zamora), 1994 (Box 1, Othertype 82)
- Man Loses His Pants During Arrest, 1978 (Box 1, Othertype 83)
- Social Unwest (rug-O-War), 1995 (Box 1, Othertype 84)
- Social Unwest (Dead on street), 1995 (Box 1, Othertype 85)
- Betty & Pat, 1979 (Box 1, Othertype 86)
- Max Benavidez In Chinatown, 1994 (Box 1, Othertype 87)
- Club Limbo (Gamboa and Max Benavidz / (photo by Diego Gamboa), 1989 (Box 1, Othertype 88)
- ChIcano Artists (Gronk, Jerry Dreva, Patssi Valdez, Carlos Almaraz, John Valdez, Willie Herman, Gamboa), 1980 (Box 1, Othertype 89)
- Mundo Meza, 1981 (Box 1, Othertype 90)
- RobertBuitron, 1984 (Box 1, Othertype 91)
- Gerardo Veiazquez, 1987 (Box 1, Othertype 92)
- ASCO, 1975 (Box 1, Othertype 93)
- Willie GarcIa, 1994 (Box 1, Othertype 94)
- WIllie Herron With His Mural The Wall That Cracked Open, 1971 (Box 1, Othertype 95)
- Richard Duardo, Barbz, Carlos Almaraz(CSULA), 1979 (Box 1, Othertype 96)
- Max Benavidez, 1994 (Box 1, Othertype 97)
- 1975 (Box 1, Othertype 98)
- Harry Gamboa Jr. wearing Chicano Power Button in East LA. / (photo by Sylvia Delgado), 1971, [Polaroid] (Box 1, Othertype 99)
- Knife Attack Victim On Downtown LA. Sidewalk, 1986 (Box 1, Othertype 100)